Finding Aid for Marguerite Harms papers, 1953-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marguerite Harms papers
1953-2003
Harms, Marguerite.
88567 Aa 2
Professor of nursing at the University of Michigan. Files relating to her professional interests, especially work on undergraduate nursing curriculum committee; also nursing course materials; professional correspondence; and Cobblestone Farm Association files.
1.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Marguerite B. Harms (Donor No. 7291 ) on January 8, 1986. Periodic additions have been received.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marguerite Shirley (Babaian) Harms was born December 10, 1923, in New Britain, Connecticut. She received her registered nursing degree from Cochran School of Nursing, St. John's Riverside Hospital, Yonkers, New York (1947), her bachelor of science from New York University (1950), and her masters of science in psychiatric nursing from the University of Michigan (1966).
Harms taught at the University of Michigan School of Nursing as an instructor from 1954 to 1959, an assistant professor from 1966/67 to 1971/72, and an associate professor from 1972/73 until her retirement in December 1985.
A member of many professional and civic organizations and committees of the University of Michigan, Harms was particularly active in the American Nurses Association and the School of Nursing Undergraduate Curriculum Committee of which she was chairperson from 1975 to 1976. She also authored many articles and chapters of nursing textbooks.
The Marguerite Babaian Harms Papers consist of materials largely relating to her career at the University of Michigan School of Nursing dating from 1954 to 1985. The collection is arranged in a single topical files series. The bulk of these files fall under the headings of Committees, Correspondence, and Course Materials. There is, in addition, biographical information, a folder on the ENACT (Environmental Action) teach-in, and files relating to her interest in Cobblestone Farm, a historic Ann Arbor landmark. The collection includes three 8mm films: tentatively identified as footage of Sonya Henie on her 1938 visit to Detroit with the Hollywood Ice Review; footage of infancy of (daughter?) Lynn, and a short film from the Detroit Tigers spring training camp at Lakeland (1960s?)
Subjects:
Cobblestone Farm (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; Harms, Marguerite.
- University of Michigan Professional files
  - Biographical (vitae, evaluations, and presentations), 1953-1983 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Faculty Development Committee (minutes and notes), May-September, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation Nursing Advisory Committee Minutes, March-May 1974 (Box 1)
    - Management in Nursing (N439) Minutes, and report, April-May 1974 (Box 1)
    - Policy Review Committee Minutes, March 1970-January 1971 (Box 1)
    - Professional and Civic Services Committee Minutes, October 1967-April 1970 (Box 1)
    - Public Relations Committee Minutes, October 1973-February 1974 (Box 1)
    - Steering Committee on Undergraduate Curriculum Task Force on Distributive nursing Practice (minutes, notes, and report), February-April 1974 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee (minutes and reports), May 1974-September 1976 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee Ad hoc Committee for Skills Inventory List (includes correspondence), May-September, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Legislative
      - American Nurses Association, July 1971-February 1983 (Box 1)
      - Federal, June 1971-June 1981 (Box 1)
      - Michigan, May 1979-June 1981 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee various task forces, October 1975-June 1976 (Box 1)
  - Course Materials
    - Human Growth and Development (N232) lectures and syllabi, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
    - Nursing and Health (N240)
      - Minutes, April 1973-January 1978 (Box 1)
      - Person Assessment Guide, May-October 1979 (Box 1)
      - Seminar Notes and Activities, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
      - Syllabi, 1973-1974
        - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
        - 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Basic Concepts of Nursing (N260-261)
      - Collaborative Research, May 1978 (Box 1)
      - Community Clinicals with Children, 1973-1985 (Box 1)
      - Environment lecture, October 1979 (Box 1)
      - Fundamental Area of Instruction Minutes, January 1984-December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Legal Aspects lectures, September-November, 1978; undated (Box 1)
      - Seminar Guides, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
      - Sexuality lecture, undated (Box 1)
    - Psychiatric Nursing (N372-N375) Clinical Orientation Schedules for Nursing 372, 374, and 375, 1966-1967; 1967-1970; 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Psychiatric Nursing (N375) Role Playing Exercises, September-October 1971 (Box 1)
    - Independent Study (N499), June 1982 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  - Environmental Action for Survival Action (ENACT), 1970 (Box 1)
  - Adaptation, 1978-1987 (Box 1)
  - Arlene Wegedus (nursing study modules), 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Irene Woodman, 1981-1993 (Box 1)
  - Nurses in Military, 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  - School of Nursing, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Nursing History Society (University of Michigan)
    - Chase, Sally, autobiography written by Alice L. Price (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 1993-2000 (Box 1)
    - Calendar: "A Century of Leadership; Nursing at the University of Michigan", 1992 (Box 1)
    - Program flyers and miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Cobblestone Farms Association
  - Board minutes and related material, 1975-2003; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1994 (Box 2)
  - Fund raising, 1977-1992 (Box 2)
  - Informational material (Box 2)
  - Planning Committee (Box 2)
  - Preservation and Decorating Committee, 1982-1994 (Box 2)
  - Restoration proposal, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Special events (Box 2)
  - Training manual, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
- Films
  - Infancy of Lynn, 8mm, color, ca. 8min
    (88567-1)
  - Dorothy -- Sonya Henie, 1938; 8mm, b/w, ca. 8 min.
    (88567-2)
  - Detroit Tigers at Lakeland Spring training, circa 1960; 8mm, color, ca. 3 min.
    (88567-3